By now, you probably understand
that communication is paramount to
a project successful landing—
it's the lifeblood of the whole project.
Communication starts before
the project even begins and
carries on steadily throughout
the remainder of the project.
In this video, I'm going to explain how
using soft skills like negotiation,
delivering messages with empathy,
and asking questions for clarity helps
to foster and strengthen communication.
We'll also discuss feedback as
a foundation for iterating on a product.
According to the Project Management
Institute, it's been found that most
projects experience a communication
breakdown of some kind,
even though project managers spend
about 90% of their time working on
communication alone.
It's in a project manager's best interest
to communicate tactfully, not only with
the members of their own organization, but
also with customers and vendors.
When done well,
strategic communication with a customer or
client can instill
a sense of confidence
that you're doing a good job and
that you're a trustworthy partner.
So how should a project manager approach
communication with a customer?
Using soft skills like negotiation,
empathetic listening, and trust building,
will help foster a good relationship
between you and your customers,
and a good project manager knows how and
when to apply these skills.
A key practice for negotiation,
empathetic listening, and
trust building is asking questions.
It's important to ask open-ended questions
and actively listen to understand
the customer's current state
versus their desired state
and what might help them get from here to
there. If you ask open-ended questions,
you'll find out where you can make
your customers feel more secure.
You'll be able to negotiate to ensure
both of your needs are met, and
you'll build the necessary trust
to have a successful partnership.
High-performing project managers set
clear expectations about when they'll
communicate certain things
to their customers.
For example,
you might want to set an expectation that
you'll provide weekly progress updates
to keep clients informed,
rather than expecting them to
come to you with questions.
When troubleshooting an issue with the
product, it might not be necessary to fill
the customer in on an issue
that won't affect the outcome.
Let's say a designer on your team quit and
you had to replace them,
you may be able to replace
that designer with a new one fairly
quickly and not even skip a beat in
your project's progress.
You can complete the task at hand without
giving the customer any additional worry.
The level of visibility between customers
and clients on a given project may vary,
and you'll have to use your judgment
regarding what's important to communicate
to your client.
Sometimes, you'll want to tell
your client if there's an issue.
If you reach a point in the project
where you can't possibly move forward
without their help and input,
you'll have to communicate the issue
to them calmly and with empathy.
Let's put this into Project Plant Pals
context, where we're troubleshooting
an issue with broken planters.
Maybe when we were putting
together our quality standards,
we left some room for supplier error and
accounted for some broken planters.
We'll say we figured an acceptable
number of broken planters was two out of
every 50.
But let's imagine that the customer
received a shipment and
there were five broken planters.
At that point,
we'll need to meet with the customer and
ask important negotiation questions.
We'll need to decide if the five broken
planters out of every 50 is an acceptable
outcome,
or we'll need to discuss whether
the customer would consider investing in
a higher tier of planters that
may be less prone to breaking.
Presenting a solution like using sturdier
planters will affect their budget, and
they'll need to adjust accordingly.
Is the customer okay with that change?
Would that lead to another trade off?
Keeping in mind that the main goal here
is customer satisfaction throughout
the negotiation process,
you'll want to be considerate of
their feelings and limitations.
You can do this by exhibiting empathy:
understanding their frustrations,
addressing them, and
finding a solution that's beneficial for
both of you.
You may have held a customer-facing
role in the past,
whether that's in a call center,
as a retail associate, as a server in
a restaurant, or any number of positions.
Even if you haven't,
you've probably been an advocate for
yourself while conversing with
a customer service representative.
Because of this,
you'll probably have a good idea of
what good customer service looks like.
Good customer service results in choosing
to go back to the same hair salon, bakery,
or coffee shop
because you liked the way
that you were treated and
the service you received
(even if you had an issue),
versus choosing not to go back to those
places if you don't receive that level
of care.
Your past experiences have taught
you to manage relationships and
to avoid delivering something
that's low quality.
It doesn't feel great when you're on the
receiving end. In order to yield better
results in future projects, it's
necessary to get feedback from customers.
Sometimes, this feedback will come
during the process, and sometimes,
it'll come after the project is completed,
depending on how you map it
out in the initiation phase.
The matter of when you receive feedback
may come down to what you actually want
to accomplish in your project.
If your business is launching
an e-commerce site,
you will want user feedback
so you can make adjustments to optimize
the customers' shopping experience.
If your business is an on-demand
cookie delivery service,
you may want to deliver the cookies
and then get user feedback to
know how your customers felt
about the cookies and
the delivery experience as a whole.
User feedback helps to close any gaps and
understanding between the customer's
expectation and the project's needs.
So to summarize very briefly, soft skills
like negotiation, empathetic listening,
and trust-building
will help create a good relationship
between you and your customers,
and getting feedback from those customers
will help you to iterate on a product or
service.
That's a lot of information—great job taking it all in!
We'll get a little more specific with user
testing and feedback in the next video.
I'll meet you there.